Guide to the Arthur B. Shostak Papers, 1976-2012 RL.11140
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Arthur B. Shostak papers
1976-2012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11140
8.0 Linear Feet
8 boxes
Arthur Shostak is a sociologist whose research focused on the topic of men and abortion. The collection documents his work, including survey results, speeches, research, clippings. and printed materials.
Biographical / Historical
Arthur Shostak (b.1937), is an American sociologist and futurist, and former professor of sociology at Drexel University. He is the author of the 1984 book, Men and Abortion: Lessons, Losses, and Love (Praeger). He retired from Drexel University in 2003.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Arthur B. Shostak papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2014-2016.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of materials related to work on men's experiences with abortion and abortion generally: research materials (clippings, articles, notes), writings and talks by Shostak and others, appearances by Shostak in magazines, newspapers, and other printed media, correspondence, conference files, ephemera and publications of clinics and other abortion-related organizations, A/V material (1 audiocassette and 2 VHS tapes), and 3 books. Surveys completed by male partners of women seeking abortions and "waiting room males" accompanying women receiving abortions in clinics between 1999 and 2012. Also included are numerical data reports and textual reports likely based on survey responses as well as a small number of print materials related to abortion and materials related to his 1984 book, Men and Abortion: Lessons, Losses, and Love (Praeger).
- Accession (2014-0186), 1976-2010
  Scope and Contents
  Collection consists of material related to work on men's experiences with abortion and abortion generally: research materials (clippings, articles, notes), writings and talks by Shostak and others, appearances by Shostak in magazines, newspapers, and other prting media, correspondence, conference files, ephemera and publications of clinics and other abortion-related organizations, A/V material (1 audiocassette and 2 VHS tapes), and 3 books.
  - Hope Clinic Study, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Research Materials: Articles, Writings, etc. (10 folders), 1986-2008 and undated (Box 1)
  - Cathy Young blog on spousal husband notification, 2005 (Box 1)
  - The Forgotten Father: Men and Abortion Life Cycle Books pamphlet, undated (Box 1)
  - New York Times Magazine: The New Abortion Providers, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Abortion and Mental Health: Facts and Myths Forum at Drexel, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Father's Legal Rights, undated (Box 1)
  - Assorted Correspondence (2 folders), 1982-1984 (Box 1)
  - Assorted Correspondence/Writings, undated (Box 1)
  - Outlook Tape, 2001 (Box 1)
  - Dispatches From the Abortion Wars: The Costs of Fanaticism to Doctors, Patients, and the Rest of Us, by Carol Joffe, 2009 (Box 2)
  - The Story of Jane: The Legendary Underground Feminist Abortion Service, by Laura Kaplan, 1995 (Box 2)
  - The Facts of Life, by Jonathan Miller and David Pelham, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Men and Abortion Thesis, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Males Who Accompany Their Partners in the Abortion Process Thesis, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Assorted Articles, Writings, Research, Correspondence (11 folders) (Box 2)
  - Abortion Clinic Surveys, undated (Box 2)
  - Male Doctors and Abortion VHS tape, undated (Box 2)
  - Men and Abortion TV Talk Show VHS tape, undated (Box 2)
  - MS Special Report Abortion, undated (Box 3)
  - Male Partners & the Psychological Sequence of Abortion, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Assorted Articles on Men & Abortion (4 folders), undated (Box 3)
- Accession (2016-0020), 1978-2012
  Addition consists of two different surveys completed by both male partners of women seeking abortions and "waiting room males" accompanying women receiving abortions in clinics between 1999 and 2012. Also included are numerical data reports and textual reports likely based on survey responses. There is also a small number of print materials related to men and abortion by both Shostak and other authors.
  Arrangement
  This addition is divided into two series: Print Materials, and Surveys and Data. The survey responses are arranged in chronological order.
  - Print Materials, 1978-2008
    - Men and Abortion: Lessons, Losses, and Love, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Shostak articles, 1979-1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Shostak article: Abortion as Fatherhood Lost: Problems and Reforms, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Articles on men and abortion, 1978-2004 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Post Abortion Counseling: A Manual for Christian Counselors, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Planned Parenthood v Casey, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Men's handwritten reflections on the abortion experience, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Surveys and Data, 1980-2012
    - Questionnaire for male partners of our clinic patients, 1999-2000
      - University of British Columbia, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Toronto, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Duluth, MN, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Preterm Clinic, Cleveland, OH, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Clinic for Women, Indianapolis, IN, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Concord Feminist Health Center, Concord, NH, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
      - Hartford GYN Center, Hartford, CT, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Hope Clinic for Women, Granite City, IL, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Allegheny Reproductive Health Center, Pittsburgh, PA, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Elizabeth Blackwell Health Center for Women, Philadelphia, PA, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Unknown locations, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 4-10)
    - Survey: Feedback from waiting room males, 2003-2010
      - Unknown locations, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 2-5)
      - Various locations, 2004 (Box 6, 7, Folder 6-11, 1-5)
      - Allentown, PA, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Indianapolis, IN, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Vestal, NY, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Fargo, ND, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Philadelphia, PA, 2004 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Philadelphia Women's Center, 2007-2010 (Box 8, Folder 2-5)
      - Unknown locations, 2008 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Various locations, 2009 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Various locations, 2012 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Statistical analysis, 1980-2003
      - Males and the abortion experience survey data, circa 1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Statistics, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 1)